hello and welcome to the Nobel Prize
award ceremony here at the Stockholm
Concert Hall here we see some of the uh
over 1,500 guests assembled here for the
prize ceremony held on December 10th as
every year the anniversary of Alfred
nobel's death Alfred Nobel that we see
here as a
statue the Swedish inventor and
industrialist who in his will created
this prize and since 1901 it's been
awarded to the people who have
contributed the most in to advances in
The Sciences of physics chemistry
medicine and to the most distinguished
authors alive and uh here we see some of
uh uh previous laurates that are uh
present here today for instance
Christian newsline vaart and uh we have
members of the Swedish Academy that uh
choose the U uh literature
Laurette who this year is uh Bob Dylan
who will not be here in person uh but
the closest we will get is his uh uh
friend and uh uh partner out on the uh
tour scene Patty Smith who will be
performing one of his songs and here we
see Angus Deon last year's economics
laurat uh here as a guest this year uh
sitting just in front of uh Swedish one
of the Swedish
authors uh who are part of the uh
cultural
uh uh establishment represented here
this
evening and uh yes as we saw uh last
year's economics Laurette reminds us
that in
1969 there since 1969 there is also a
prize in economics the Swedish Central
bank's prize in economic Sciences in
memory of Alfred Nobel and in total five
prizes will be delivered from the hands
of his majesty the king of Sweden here
today celebrating five disciplines with
10 excellent scientists and one very
special literature Laurette as I said
earlier Bob Dylan uh and yes well he
won't be here in person but he has said
that the news about the Nobel Prize left
me speechless and he also said that he
appreciates the honor so
much in a little while we will hear
presentation speeches about uh this
year's prizes and uh They will receive
uh the laurates will receive their
medals and diplomas one by one from the
hand of his majesty the king of
Sweden we lay our eyes on this year's
floral
arrangement uh which is as the tradition
has it flowers sent here from the city
of Sano the place where Alfa Nobel lived
during the last years of his life in
total 22,000 flowers
300 kilos of green leaves giving a
feeling of spring on the stage this year
pink uses dominate as you can see
inspired by Japanese cherry blossoms we
do have a Japanese laurate this year uh
in medicine physi physiology or medicine
the prize is awarded to honor Professor
yoshinori ome
me and we will hear some music as well
the Royal Stockholm pH monic Orchestra
under the patn of conductor Marie renir
will provide musical interludes during
the award ceremony Marie is a versatile
musician and one of soon's most
promising young
conductors and uh The Soloist at the
award ceremony is Patty Smith she will
perform a hard rain zag Fall by this
year's literature laor Bob Dylan and
here we see some of the Swedish Party
leaders in the center this sish uh right
party right-wing party uh anashin by
bartra and her husband to the left there
and
uh among the 1500 guests are of course
the Nobel laurates and their family and
friends each of them can bring uh 15
persons in total to the priz ceremony
and the banquet but some have uh come to
Stockholm with a lot more uh friends uh
I think that U one of them has no less
than 68 friends in his his company
here's here we see some more uh party
leaders from the Swedish uh Parliament
and we also have Representatives uh from
uh the academic uh Society such as uh
the awarding uh bodies of the Nobel
Foundation we are waiting for the
royal family to
enter uh they are uh they will sit on on
stage and there we will have his uh
Majesty the king of Sweden and queen
Sylvia and Crown Princess Victoria and
her husband Prince
Daniel so those are the four seats that
uh are to the right the Royal seats
and the chairman of the board of the
Nobel Foundation Professor Carl Henry
Kine will hold an opening address uh
after which this year's Nobel laurates
uh will be
presented and we have uh had the priz
ceremony here in Stockholm's Concert
Hall
uh for many many years uh and the
tradition has it that afterwards uh the
guests go uh a short distance to uh the
uh City Hall where the banquet commences
around 7:00 this evening Swedish
time now we see members of the royal
family Prince call philli and his wife
Princess Sophia entering
here as uh princess meline and her
husband Christopher Mr Christopher
on now time for the Swedish Royal
Anthem his majesty the king of Sweden
entering with queen
syvia crown Princess Victoria and Prince
Daniel
[Music]
[Applause]
sish Minister
St with his
[Music]
[Applause]
wife
[Music]
the Royal Phil harmonics performing a
March in D Major by wolf Kang amados
[Music]
mosite under the bath of Mar and
me and to this Mar we have the L Nobel
laurates entering here physics Laurette
David
thus followed by physics laurate Duncan
halane and physics laurate Michael
cix and then chemistry laurate
jeanpierre Sage followed by Fraser stot
and chemics
laurate Ben
[Music]
finga
Duncan
howan this year's medicine laurate
yoshinori Os from
Japan followed by this year's two
economics laurates Mr Oliver Hart and
Bank
holmstrom
[Music]
David
thus Duncan
hame and Michael citz
physics the chemistry
chairs jeanpier Sage from France who
works in
stasbor Fraser
stod and Ben f
j
Yosh medicine
La Oliver
Hart at Harvard and B Holstrom at MIT
this year's economics
laurat
[Music]
and now time for what we came here
for your majesties your Royal
highnesses esteemed Nobel laurates
ladies and gentlemen Professor K on
behalf of the Noel Foundation it's a
great pleasure for me to welcome you all
to this year's Nobel Prize award
ceremony which is held to honor the
laurates for their outstanding
contributions to science and
literature in particular I would like to
wish the Nobel laurates and their
families welcome to the
ceremony earlier today in Oslo President
Juan Manuel Santos received the Nobel
Peace Prize for his Resolute efforts to
bring the more than 50 yearlong Civil
War in Colombia to an
end we are gathered here today to honor
science humanism and peaceful
coexistence we are here as individuals
not as representatives of States groups
or
interests in
1895 Alfred Nobel wrote In His will that
no con consideration should be given to
nationality that the most worthy should
receive the
prize Nobel himself was born in Sweden
but worked abroad for much of his life
in St Petersburg in Paris and in
Sano he spoke five languages and worked
with people from different cultures with
different religious
backgrounds Nobel was a true
Cosmopolitan convinced of the value of
extensive crossb
contacts Alfred Nobel was also
influenced by the new Enlightenment a
period during the late 19th century when
new political ideas
emerged there was strong optimism which
was manifested in recurring World
exhibitions spectacular structures like
the Eiffel Tower and arenas for peace
International competitions such as the
Olympic
Games it was also an era of Rapid
economic expansion with millions of
people being rescued from poverty thanks
to industrialization and
Entrepreneurship meanwhile it was also
an era that was strongly shaped by
nationalism xenophobia and Military
threats developments that would
culminate in the horrendous first World
War
much of of what was topical for Alfred
Nobel in the late 19th century also
characterizes the world of
today billions of people have been
lifted out of poverty by globalization
and international trade many people
around the world are addressing major
challenges facing Humanity researchers
are making fantastic scientific
discoveries authors and Poets are
writing about difficult existential
issues
and dedicated leaders are making efforts
to achieve
peace these are contributions that we
are rewarding today with the Nobel
Prize but just as in the era of Alfred
Nobel today there are dark clouds in the
sky around the
world terrorist acts are a part of many
people's daily lives and Wars are
underway in many
places International cooperation
crossborder movements and openness are
being
criticized science and knowledge are
being questioned for instance regarding
climate
change leading politicians both in
Europe and in the US are winning votes
by denying knowledge and scientific
truths populism is widespread and is
reaping major political
successes the Grim truth is that we can
no longer take for granted that people
believe in science facts and
knowledge in times like these the Nobel
Prize is
important Alfred Nobel wanted to reward
those who have conferred the greatest
benefit to
mankind he understood the power of
example and this is a central concept
behind his
will good Role Models show by their
words and deeds that it is possible to
understand the world and to improve it
they confirm that people can tackle the
biggest challenges of our
era doing so requires creative and
courageous individuals who are willing
to take the lead find Solutions and
broaden our
awareness Alfred Nobel wanted the Nobel
Prize to contribute to a better world
and he wanted us to be inspired by the
Nobel laurates and what they have
achieved for
Humanity this is why we have developed
public activities over the past 20 years
that are based on all this accumulated
knowledge and which should Inspire
learning reflection and
questioning during the days when the
2016 lates were being announced 100
million people engaged with us through
our digital
channels there is an enormous interest
in learning about the scientific and
humanistic advances that are rewarded
with the Nobel
Prize in light of this we're pleased
that the new Nobel Center the Nobel
prize's own building is about to take
shape here in Stockholm the Nobel Center
will be a place where the fascinating
stories of the Nobel laurits and their
discoveries will be at display it will
also be a global platform with education
knowledge and CR itical thinking at its
heart where the major challenges of
Tomorrow will be
discussed Alber kamu who received the
1957 Nobel Prize in literature said that
the 17th century was the century of
mathematics the 18th that of the
physical sciences and the 19th that of
biology our 20th century is the century
of fear the 21st century has begun with
a growing sense of fear and there is a
concern that conflicts will characterize
this Century as
well but such a development is not
predestined it is our task to influence
how our era will be described and there
are good reasons to be
hopeful we see a growing interest among
young people in seeking knowledge and we
see an ever increasing engagement in
tackling major Global challenges
this is where the Nobel Prize has an
important task to serve as a source of
inspiration for people who want to build
a better
world this is the truly amazing Legacy
left by Alfred Noel 120 years after his
death your majesties your Royal
highnesses
esteemed Nobel laurates ladies and
gentlemen thank you for listening and
once again most welcome to this year's
no Nobel Prize award ceremony those were
the words of uh Professor call Henry kin
chairman of the board of the Nobel
Foundation now a small musical interlude
quad from the wedding of the Eiffel
Tower by jaman
tyer
[Music]
[Applause]
and now time for Professor Thor Hans
Hanson
who is member of the royal Student
Academy of Sciences and also member of
the Nobel committee for physics to
present this year's Nobel Prize in
physics
your majesties your Ro highnesses esteem
Nobel
laurates dear colleagues in the
International Community of Scholars
ladies and
gentlemen physique physics is a human
activity like all such activities it
evolves in the context of historical
Geographic and linguis I settings
nonetheless the central results of
physics natural laws transcend these
barriers they are the same today as they
were at Inception and they will also be
valid in the
future they are the same here on Earth
as on the Exotic planets that we now
know are orbiting distant Stars the laws
of physics are Universal and they are
formulated in the language of
mathematics extraordinary universality
is closely connected to the fundamental
properties of space time and
matter which are reflected in the form
of symmetries in the laws of physics a
branch of mathematics used to describe
symmetries is called group Theory and
was substantially developed during the
19th century only later did this
mathematics turn out to be an
indispensable tool in the new quantum
theory that revolutionized physics
during the 20th
century the role of group theory in
quantum mechanics is but one example of
how major scientific breakthroughs often
require new
language and since the language of
physics is mathematical breakthroughs in
physics often require new
mathematics Newton developed the theory
of derivatives and integrals at the same
time as his
mechanics and Stein formulated his
general theory of relativity in terms of
the den contemporary mathematics of
curved spaces which was unfamiliar to
physicists mathematical language is
abstract but it has two major
virtues a mathematically formulated
theory is quantitative and can therefore
often be used to in detail and with high
Precision explain and predict the
results of
mathematics is deductive so mathematical
arguments can be used to predict the
results of future
experiments the discovery of the Hig
particle is a striking example deduction
is indeed an important tool in all the
Sciences but it excels in theoretical
physics
many philosophers physicists and
mathematicians have marveled at the
astonishing ability of mathematics to
describe nature in a famous essay Eugene
vigner called
this the unreasonable effectiveness of
mathematics this year's Nobel Prize in
physics rewards contributions to
theoretical physics that are examples of
precisely this unreasonable
effectiveness
by using new Concepts taken from the
branch of mathematics called
topology the 2016 laurates did two
things first they explained striking
observations and second they made
theoretical discoveries that is they
predicted new phenomena that were
observed later topology describes the
robust properties of objects
topologically an egg and a football
belong to the same category the category
of three dimensional objects without
holes but a donut along with a wedding
ring belongs to the category of objects
with one hole the number of holes which
is always an integer is an example of a
topological
invariant
inant mechan quantum mechanics was born
as a Theo microscopic objects individual
atoms and molecules but it also soon
came to be used in order to understand
the usual phases of matter gases liquids
and
solids super fluids and super conductors
were also added to these here too
symmetry Concepts proved extremely
important by studying symmetry
properties Leva was able to classify
possible phases of matter and describe
the mechanisms of the transitions
between
them this year's laurates showed that
L's classification of the phases of
matter was
incomplete there are additional
so-called topological phases with
characteristic values for different
topological
invariance with the aid of topolog
topology they also showed how one can
explain observe transitions between
different phases of matter that should
not be possible according to earlier
Theory it often takes time before new
Concepts and new ways of thinking have
an
impact but during the past decade
research in the topological faces of
matter has virtually
exploded today's Young physicists work
with topological Concepts as
self-confidently and skillfully as
earlier Generations have done with
derivatives symmetries and
geometry not only have this year's
laurates made important special
discoveries but in addition and perhaps
most importantly they have set the stage
for a new way of describing
matter they have given us a rich
mathematical language with deep and
beautiful abstract
Concepts but in the Natural Sciences
beauty is not enough mathematics is full
of beautiful
results truth is also necessary this
requires experiments and measurements
the theory of ological matter has passed
this test with
distinction it combines truth with
beauty this is theoretical
physics at its
best Professor thus professor halane
professor
CIT you have
been you have been a awarded the Nobel
Prize in physics for I quote the
citation theoretical discoveries of
topological phase transition and
topological phes of matter on behalf of
the royal Swedish Academy of Sciences is
my honor and my pleasure to convey to
you the warmest
congratulations I now ask you to step
forward to receive you Nobel prizes from
the hands of his majesty the king
first Professor David
thus us and British citizen born in 1934
in the United Kingdom he is affiliated
with the University of Washington in the
US receiving the diploma and the
medal from the hands of his majest the
king of
Sweden
[Applause]
Professor Duncan HDE now also British
citizen born in 1951 in the United
Kingdom he is affiliated with Princeton
University in the
US
[Music]
[Applause]
this now time for Professor Michael
calitz us and British citizen born in
1943 in the United Kingdom he is
Affiliated now with Brown University in
the
US
congratulated by
[Applause]
[Music]
King family and friends enjoying this
moment in the
audience
after the Prize in physics is time to
present the prize in
chemistry professor Olf rstr it is my it
is
majesties Royal Highness your
excellencies ladies and
gentlemen
machines are an integral part of human
development helping us to perform tasks
that often fall beh beyond your cap our
capacities over the
Millennia our society has enjoyed an
ever increasing plethora of useful
machines for various purposes in many
ways leading to an enhanced quality of
Our Lives this progress has in
particular accelerated since the
Industrial Revolution with its key
discoveries resulting in a giant Le
forward and dramatically changing the
world
today we are at the dawn of a new reev
Revolution that will bring us yet
another giant leap forward humankind has
always striven to push the limits of
machine function and construction for
example regarding how small they can be
made the ultimate limit of this endeavor
is to make molecular sized machine
structures that are less than a
thousandth of the width of a human
hair this
fundamental challenge has been met by
this year's laurates who have
successfully demonstrated that their
rational design and synthesis of
molecular machines are indeed
possible the groundbreaking step in this
development was taken in the early 1980s
when je sage and his group discovered an
efficient way to make molecules that are
attached to each other using mechanical
bonds
the group that thus managed to link two
molecular rings together in a so-called
katame where the Rings could move freely
relative each without being separated
this marked a breakthrough towards
molecular machinery and Sage was able to
show how such structures can undergo
controlled
motion by the turn of the
1990s Fraser stot as we see here and his
group made other important advances
towards molecular machinery for example
the group used another type of
mechanical Bond and developed socaled
rotaxanes in which a ring shaped
molecule was tied to move between set
POS positions along an
axle both stodart and
Sage were also able to show how the
movement in these structures could be
controlled from external input and
subsequent ly developed a wide range of
machine like structures such as
molecular muscles actuators elevators
memories Motors and
pumps the motor components are of
central importance in machines able to
drive other parts of the
construction by the late 1990s Ben
finger and his group made a significant
breakthrough when they demonstrated a
molecular rotary
motor the construction was driven by
light and heat and was based on
isomerizable bonds and molecular
asymmetry where the motor parts could
rotate unidirectionally relative each
other the group was later able to
improve the design to create Motors that
can rotate in either direction at very
high speeds and showed how the
components can affect the rotation of
much larger
objects in
playful example FAS group also
constructed a four-wheel drive nanocar
that can move over a
surface through the design and synthesis
of very challenging structures combined
with the understanding and development
of controlled motion and
function
sage and have created functional
molecular
machines the work has formed the basis
for an entirely New Field of research
for which the three laurates have been
groundbreaking pioneers and sources of
inspiration
Shier and B
finga you are being awarded the Nobel
Prize in chemistry for the design and
synthesis of molecular
machines on behalf of the royal Swedish
Academy of Sciences I wish to convey to
you our warmest congratulations may I
now ask you to step forward and receive
your Nobel prizes from the hands of his
majesty the
king first Professor jeanpier Sage a
French citizen born in 1944 in France
affiliated with the University of
stasbor in
[Music]
[Applause]
France
Professor frasa stodart is a us and
British citizen born in 19422 in the
United Kingdom and now affiliated with
Northwestern University in the
[Music]
[Applause]
US
he here stocking accompanied by his two
daughters and their families including
four
grandchildren Professor Bernard finga is
a Dutch citizen born in 1951 in the
Netherlands affiliated with the
University of groan in the
[Music]
Netherlands
[Applause]
he's here in Stockholm with his wife
Elizabeth RMA three daughters and other
family
members now time for some music again we
will hear Orford Ness from the Suffolk
site by dorine
kwi
performed by the uh Royal philarmonic
Orchestra conductor Mari
[Music]
Ren
Prince called philli and his uh
wife
sopia
Prin
[Music]
kust silia and
Prin
now time for the Nobel Prize in
physiology or
medicine as it is called the medicine
prize presented by Professor n laon from
K Institute at a member of Nobel
committee for the medicine
prize yeah there my
majesties your Royal highnesses esteemed
laurates ladies and
gentlemen today we have gathered for the
awarding of this year's Nobel Prize in
the Stockholm Concert Hall one of
Sweden's architectural masterpieces
which was inaugurated in
1926 the concert hall is in good shape
despite intensive use over many decades
thanks to repairs and
maintenance today it is also newly
cleaned and
spotless the consumables that previous
guests have left behind have been
collected and hopefully
recycled we view this daily maintenance
as something
self-evident but if the concert hall had
not been repaired or cleaned in 90 years
this would of course have been obvious
to
us similarly our body's cells are
constantly replacing defective
components and removing waste material
this year's Nobel Prize in physiology or
medicine is about how the cell maintains
its interior and recycles its own
components in order to function
optimally and adapt to new
circumstances the
cells degradation station the lome was
identified by biochemical methods as
early as 1955 by the Belgian scientist
Christian for this discovery he was
awarded the Nobel Prize in physiology of
medicine in
1974 shortly after the discovery of the
lisome several researchers using
electron micros microscopy showed that
lomes seem to exist in all organisms
having nucleated cells they also
observed that lomes could sometimes be
full of normal cellular components in
various stages of
decomposition remarkably it appeared as
if the cell could break down some of its
own
contents in 1963 chrisan named this
process
autoag which which means self
eaing in the following decades some
progress was made in our understanding
of aagi but fundamental questions remain
remained unanswered
is autophagy crucial to normal cell
function if so how is autophagy
regulated is oophagy important in human
disease when
Yosi we see here was in his early 40s he
was eager to make new major scientific
advances in the late 1980s he therefore
decided to take on a whole new area of
research
degradation
processes alome predicted that
degradation might very well be a
processed just as important as the
production of new components in a Cell
for his studies he chose to use
ordinary baker's
yeast yeast cells are
unicellular
[Music]
UK nucleated organism that can be used
as a model systems for understanding
fundamental processes also find in human
cells by employing a brilliant
experimental strategy OSI was able to
show that autoag actually does occur in
yeast he then carried out a series of
very elegant studies that enable him to
identify a number of genes that are
vital in regulating
Auto omei went on to show new completely
unexpected biochemical mechanisms that
are controlled by these genes it also
soon turned out that the cellular
Machinery that controls autoag is highly
conserved and is found in all organisms
contain nucleated
cells the discovery of the molecular
Machinery of autoi revolutionized 's
entire field of
research and we know today that autoa is
a very important maintenance process
that ensures the normal functioning of
our cells
for example autophagic plays a key role
when we adjust our metabolism to fasting
and
starvation impairments in the regulation
of autopi are linked to a variety of
human diseases such as diabetes cancer
infections and severe disorders of the
nervous
system thanks to aom's fundamental
discoveries we now know that autophagy
plays a fundamental role in many
different bi
processes
process Professor
OSI your groundbreaking research has
solved a longstanding Enigma in
biology and revealed mechanisms for how
ourselves recycle components and combat
disease with a series of brilliant
experiments you have opened up a new
Fielding
biology on behalf of the Nobel assembly
at kolin instituted it is my great
privilege to convey to you our warmest
congratulations I now ask you to step
forward to receive your Nobel prize from
the hands of his majesty the
king honor Professor yoshinori o
Japanese citizen born in 1945 in Japan
is affiliated with the Tokyo Institute
of
Technology
[Applause]
and here is his wife Maro
ome and his two sons who join him here
in stockall for this proud
moment now we will hear a serenade from
King Christian the second Suite by Jean
[Music]
celus
l
[Music]
h
[Applause]
[Music]
all
the Royal philonic Orchestra performing
serenade from King Crystal the second
Suite by finish composer C so we will
hear music of a different kind uh
something that a lot of people
probably have heard
before performed by Patty Smith because
now time for the literature prize
presented by Horus engall member of the
Swedish
Academy
your majesties your Royal
highnesses your
excellencies ladies and
gentlemen what brings about the great
shift in the world of
literature often it is when someone
seizes upon a simple overlooked for
discounted as art in the highest sense
and makes it
mutate thus at one point emerged the
modern novel from anecdote and
letter thus arose drama in a new age
from high Jinx on planks placed on
barrels in the marketplace does songs in
the vernacular the throne learned Latin
poetry thus too did laon take animal
fables and H Christian Anderson fairy
tales from the nursery to panasian
Heights each time this
occurs our idea of
literature
changes in itself it ought not to be
Sensation that a singer songwriter now
stands recipient of the liter literary
Nobel
Prize in a distant past all poetry was
sung or tunefully recited poet were rap
BS
Trad lyrics comes from Le L uh but what
Bob Dylan did was not to return to the
Greeks or the provinal instead he
dedicated himself body and soul to 20th
century American popular music the kind
played on radio stations and gramophone
records for ordinary people white and
black
protest
songs country
Blues early Rock gospel mainstream
music he listened day and night testing
the stuff on his instruments trying to
learn but when he started to write
similar songs they came out differently
in his hands the material changed from
what he discovered in Halo and
scrap in banal rhyme and quick wit in
curses and Pierce
prayers sweet nothings and crude jokes
he pan poetry gold whether on purpose or
by accident is irrelevant all creativity
begins in
imitation even after 50 years of in
uninterrupted exposure we are yet to
absorb music's equivalent of the fable
Flying
Dutchman he makes good Rhymes said a
Critic explaining
greatness and it is
true his rhyming is an
Al alchemical substance that dissolves
context to create new ones scarcely
containable by the human brain it was a
shock with a public expecting poppy folk
songs there stood a young man with a
guitar fusing the languages of the
street and the Bible into a compound
that would have made the end of the
world seem a Superfluous
replay at the same time he sang of love
with the power of conviction everyone
wants to
own all of a sudden much of the bookish
Poetry in our world felt
anemic and the routine song lyrics his
colleagues contined to write were like
oldfashioned gunpowder following the
invention of dynamite
soon people stopped comparing him to wri
and Hank Williams and turned instead to
Blake Rambo Witman
Shakespeare in the most unlikely setting
of all the commercial gramophone record
he gave back to the language of poetry
its elevated style lost since the
romantics not to sing of eternities but
to speak of what was happening around
us as if the Oracle of delie were
reading the Evening
News recognizing that Revolution by
awarding Bob Dillan the Nobel Prize was
a decision that seemed daring only
beforehand and already seems
obvious but does he get the prize for
upsetting the system of
literature
no not
really there is a simpler
explanation one that we share with all
those who stand with beating hearts in
front of the stage at one of the venues
on his never ending
tour waiting for that magical voice Shan
made the observation that when a master
such as La Fontan appears the hierarchy
of genres the estimation of what is
great and small high and low in
literature is is
nullified what matter the rank of a work
when its beauty is of the highest rank
we
wrote that is the straight answer to the
question of how Bob Dyan belongs in
literature as the beauty of his songs is
of their highest
rank by means of his Bob Dylan has
changed our idea of what poetra can be
and how it can work he is a singer
worthy of a place beside the
Greeks beside over beside the Romantic
Visionaries beside the kings and queens
of the
Blues beside the Forgotten masters of
brilliant standards if people in the
letter literary World grown one must
remind that the gods don't write they
dance and they
sing the good wishes of the Swedish
Academy follow Mr Dylan on his way to
coming dance
dan
[Music]
where you been my blue W
Sun where have you been my darling young
one I've stumbled alongside of 12 Misty
Mountains I've walked and I've crawled
down six crooked
highways I've stepped in the middle of
seven sad
Forest been out in front of a dozen dead
oceans been 10,000 miles on the mouth of
a
graveyard it's a
hard it's a
hard it's a h
Rings going to
fall what did you see my blueeyed son
what did you see my darling young
one so a newborn babe with wild wolves
all around it saw the highway of
diamonds with nobody on it I saw the
Black branch with blood that kept
dripping I saw the babe that was is just
bleeding I saw a bab
that I'm
sorry
Earth all
tin
sorry I'm sorry could we start that
section I apologize sorry I'm so
nervous
[Music]
so a newborn Bay with wild wolves all
around it s a highway of diamonds with
nobody on
it I saw the Black branch with blood
that kept dripping
saw the room full of men whose hammers
were
bleeding I saw the white lad all covered
with
water saw 10,000 talkers whose tongues
were all
broken I all guns and sharp swords in
the hands of young
children and it's a
heart it's a
heart it's a heart
it's a h
Rings going a
[Music]
fall what did you hear my blueeyed
son and what did you hear my darling
young
one heard the sound of a thunder that
roared out a warning
heard the Roar of a wave that could
drown the whole
world heard one person laughing heard
many people
laughing
heard nobody
listening heard one person starve heard
many people
laughing heard the song of a poet who
died in the
gutter heard the sound of a clown that
cried in the
alley it's a
heart it's a
heart it's a heart
ring going to
fall who did you meet my bluee
sun and who did did you meet my darling
young
one I'm met a young child beside a dead
Pony I met a young man and had a black
dog I met a young woman whose body was
burning I met a young girl she gave me
rainbow a made Young
man he was wounded in
love I met another man he was wounded in
hatred it's a
heart it's a
heart it's a heart
ring going to
fall
[Music]
and what do you do now my blue wide
son and what do you do now my darling
young
one I'm going back yeah for the rain
starts of
falling I'm going down deep in the
deepest black
fire where the people are many and their
hands are all
empty where the pellets of poison are
flooded their
Waters we're home in the Valley meets
The Damp dirty
prison and The Executioner's face is
always will it
where hunger is ugly where souls are
forgotten where black is the color where
none is the
number and I'll tell it and think it and
speak it and breathe it and reflect from
the mountains so All Souls can see it
and I'll Stand in the ocean until I
start
sinking and I'll know my soul well if I
singing it's
heart it's
hard it's a
heart it's a
heart it's a heart
R are going to
[Music]
fall
and now time for the uh presentation of
uh the economics prize here we have
professor at the edge of the
Mediterranean outside today's isir in
Turkey the Greek city of teos was
located in ancient times during recent
excavations of that City archaeologists
discovered a one and a half meter high
white
marble with a 50 line long chiseled
inscription it turned out to be a 2,200
years old lease agreement for a property
including buildings farmland and associ
slaves a wealthy man in t had donated
the property to a nearby gymnasium but a
students who were busy with their
studies and sports Leed it out to the
highest
bidder one clause in the detailed
agreement gave the owners the right to
inspect yearly whether the tenant was
keeping the buildings in good repair and
taking good care of the farmer more than
half of the lines of the inscription
listed the extra fees and
that could be charged to the tenant in
case of aach of
contract the agreement also gave the
owners the right to hold religious
ceremonies on the property three days
per year this not only provided the
students with spiritual sustenance but
also made their rental income
taxfree in other words even the ancient
Greeks had written contracts with each
other in today's society contracts are
even more important we enter into job
contracts with employees and loan
contracts with banks and we buy
insurance to protect protect ourselves
against theft and accidents the most
successful of us can write Wills
including Provisions that are maintained
for more than 100
years contracts may be long and full of
fine print but they can also be simple
and or implied such as the weekly
allowance we promise to give our
children if they clean their rooms
contracts also regulate non-economic
relationships at all levels of society
from marriage to constitutional laws to
International
treaties contracts can make us think of
unpleasantness and arguments the tenant
in teos had to accept stringent Clauses
and threatening sanctions yet the
fundamental aim of contracts is
cooperation a well-written agreement
creates a golden compromise between
parties with partly Divergent interests
entering into agreements is a difficult
art poorly designated agreements can
lead to deception and unnecessary
conflict well-drafted contracts however
encourage each party to act in a way
that benefits everyone this year's price
in economic Sciences is being awarded
for theories about writing good
contracts contracts usually specify
payments for certain behaviors or
outcomes Bank holstroms work examines
both the benefits and drawbacks of such
economic
rewards a variable salary can cause us
to become more goal oriented and to work
harder but it can also make us assume
excessive risks focus on the wrong
things and become less enthusiastic
about our work Holstrom has also shown
how contracts should be adjusted when
the parties will be working together
over a long period of time and how good
agreements can encourage an individual
even though only team performance can be
observed one common denominator is that
contracts must be balanced and adapted
to the specific
situation the future is often too comp
and unpredictable for a contract to be
able to describe all conceivable
circumstances in that case the contract
can regulate who has the right to make
decisions in what situations Oliver
Hart's research on incomplete contracts
deals with how decision- making rights
should be
allocated among other things his Works
provide us with a rich theory of
property
rights perhaps it would have been better
for the students in TS if they had sold
their property to the talent and saved
themselves to trouble to caring out 50
lines of ancient Greek text in Marble
heart's toolkit can be used to
understand where the two companies
should merge how to design an effective
bankruptcy law and whether to operate a
particular welfare service in the
private or public
sector dear professors har and
Holstrom the blossoming field of
contract theory stands firmly on the
shoulders of your
contributions with the tools of this
Theory we can better understand many
real world contracts and contractual
institutions but more importantly your
work helps us write better contracts to
enhance cooperation and Welfare so your
research is an outstanding example of
practically useful theory in the best
sense of the
term it's an honor and a privilege to
convey to you on behalf of the royal
Swedish of Sciences our warmest
congratulations I now ask you to receive
your prizes from his majesty the
king now it's time for King call Gustav
to give the diploma and medal to
Professor Oliver Hart a us and British
citizen born in the UK and currently uh
living in the US uh aili with Harvard
University
there
the expert on incomplete
contracts he is here with his wife when
we saw there Rita Goldberg and Professor
Bank holmstrom a finished citizen born
in 1949 in Finland uh he is also in the
US at the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology
MIT here is here
today his
wife
HR and his son Sam and golden Jess and
Sam to the
left as well as friends and colleagues
Jo and now we listen to the Swedish
national
anthen
[Music]
the Swedish king and queen sing the
national
g central banks um director part
of right
standing to the right of the right
party and here we have members of the
SSH Acy awarding the literature
prize SSH minister of culture Al B can't
that
[Music]
establishment now the priz ceremony is
over the laurates have received their
Nobel
prices and time for
the king and queen to lead the
stage to the queen of festivity
[Music]
March this is played while the guests
are here in
stock
[Music]
doctor Mar
r
[Music]
the laurates are congratulated by the
uh Academy awarding the literature prize
and the other scientific bodies of the
Nobel
Foundation of physics chemistry and
medicine and also um the economics prize
which uh was instituted in 1969 by the
Central Bank
[Music]
[Applause]
memor here and also uh present this
evening are some of the previous La uh
that you might see here such as St
sh7 also
have 2004
andari Len chemics laurate 1987 present
Len he is a friend of from
survive also some medicine laurate uh
for instance B son who received it in
1982 and uh you might have spotted also
2006 Year's Peace Prize laurate Muhammad
yunus and Medicine laurate of 2009
Elizabeth Blackburn sitting up here on
the
Pod we see here Bank tomm strum
and Oliver Hart and to the right there
uh we have a glimpse of previous year's
economics story at
Angus the guests uh are now leaving uh
for the stockhom city hall where the uh
banquet is
held which begins in a couple of hours a
wonderful banquet that will last for
more than 4 hours was where the laurates
will hold speeches of
thanks and uh finally go up and have a
dance or two before they will move on to
the Nobel night C which is sort of an
Afterparty held by one of the uh
universities in
Stockholm and uh now we say thank you
very much for joining us here in
Stockholm and have a nice
evening
[Music]
you
I
e
yummy
[Music]
y
e
come
your
ch
my
than
am
[Music]
for
ni
you
it's funny
dad
is your
husband okay so we get we'll get to me
later
okay
like I
enjo I
enjo
go next
one
be